Inventory of the William Van Til papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Journals edited by William Van Til, 1946-1984
  - Phi Delta Kappan, 1970
    - Correspondence, 1970 (Folder 42: 17)
    - Drafts of articles, 1970 (Folder 42: 18)
  - The Professional Educator, correspondence, 1983-1984 (Folder 42: 19)
- Speeches and Writings, 1937-1988
  - "Freedom for Intercultural Education," draft, 1953 October (Folder 43: 1)
  - With Robert S. Gilchrist, "Social Education Textbooks," printed copy, 1942 February (Folder 43: 2)
  - Miscellaneous book reviews, drafts, 1937-1942 (Folder 43: 3)
  - Review of James B. Conant, The American High School Today, printed copy, 1959 (Folder 43: 4)
  - Review of Howard W. Odum, American Social Problems: An Introduction to the Study of the People and Their Dilemmas, draft, 1939 November (Folder 43: 5)
  - Review of books on the future of education, correspondence and printed copy, 1969 February (Folder 43: 6)
  - Review of Exploring the Little Rivers of New Jersey, printed copy, 1942 November 1 (Folder 43: 7)
  - Review of Thomas H. Robinson, Men, Groups, and the Community, printed copy, 1942 January 14 (Folder 43: 8)
  - Review of Sigmund Livingston, Must Men Hate? draft, 1944 December (Folder 43: 9)
  - Review of Eugene C. Barker and Henry Steele Commager, Our Nation, printed copy, 1942 January (Folder 43: 10)
  - Brief reviews written for Peabody Journal of Education, drafts, 1956 (Folder 43: 11)
  - Review of Howard Bloomfield, Sailing to the Sun, printed copy, 1942 December 6 (Folder 43: 12)
  - Brief reviews written for Educator's Desk Encyclopedia, correspondence and drafts, 1980 (Folder 43: 13)
  - Letter to the editor, Journal of Curriculum Theorizing, correspondence and printed copy, 1988 (Folder 43: 14)
  - "Intercultural Education," drafts, 1960 (Folder 43: 15)
- Correspondence, 1968-1982
  - American Educators' Encyclopedia, 1982 (Folder 43: 16)
  - Contemporary Education, 1968-1971 (Folder 43: 17)
- Article by Jon Van Til, "People Are People," draft and printed copy, 1955 July (Folder 43: 18)
- Speeches and Writings, 1939-1990
  - My Way of Looking at It, 1990
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Folder 44: 1)
    - Proofs, 1990 (Folder 44: 2-10)
    - Proofs, 1990 (Folder 45: 1-6)
  - Writing for Professional Publication, proofs, 1980 (Folder 45: 7-9)
  - "The Nashville Story," correspondence and printed copy, 1958 May (Folder 46: 1)
  - "The Nine Crucial Issues in Secondary Education," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1976 May (Folder 46: 2)
  - "The Peabody Plan: Administration and Faculty Establish Four New Divisions in Education," draft and printed copy, 1951 October (Folder 46: 3)
  - "Is Progressive Education Obsolete?" printed copy, 1962 May (Folder 46: 4)
  - "Of Protons, Planes, and Presley," correspondence and printed copy, 1957 May (Folder 46: 5)
  - "Post-War Problems," draft, 1942-1943 (Folder 46: 6)
  - "Rights and Responsibilities: As Citizens and Teachers," correspondence and printed copy, 1954 January (Folder 46: 7)
  - Drafts and printed copies of selected articles, 1939-1942 (Folder 46: 8)
  - "Raising Confidence in Schools," printed copy, 1981 May (Folder 46: 9)
  - "The Relevant Teacher," correspondence, 1970 (Folder 46: 10)
  - "Instructional Methods in Intercultural and Intergroup Education," draft and printed copy, 1959 October (Folder 46: 11)
  - "The Role of a Review Council," correspondence and printed copy, 1976 September (Folder 46: 12)
  - "School Council: An Adventure in Real Education," draft, 1939 May (Folder 46: 13)
  - "Schools Count in Their Communities," draft, 1941 June 1 (Folder 46: 14)
  - "Supervising Computerized Instruction," correspondence and drafts, 1969 October (Folder 46: 15)
  - "The Temper of the Times," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1969 January (Folder 47: 1)
  - "To Walk with Others," printed copy, 1969 December (Folder 47: 2)
  - "Emeritus in Retrospect: Two Great Teachers," printed copy, 1984 (Folder 47: 3)
  - "Youth Visits Industrial Detroit," printed copy, 1939 October 15 (Folder 47: 4)
  - "War Adaptations in the Guinea Pigs' School," draft and printed copy, 1943 April (Folder 47: 5)
  - "Toward Democratic Human Relations," drafts, 1946 January 17 (Folder 47: 6)
  - "We Went to Europe as a Family," drafts, 1961 (Folder 47: 7)
  - "What I Have Learned," printed copy, 1986 (Folder 47: 8)
  - "What Is the Educator's Responsibility with Respect to Controversial Issues?" draft and printed copy, 1953 April (Folder 47: 9)
  - "What Knowledge Is of Most Worth?-A Reassessment," correspondence and draft, 1965 February (Folder 47: 10)
  - "What Makes a Good High School Curriculum?" correspondence and printed copy, 1964 October (Folder 47: 11)
  - "Who Is Being Heard on Education Today?" printed copy, 1961 May (Folder 47: 12)
  - "William Heard Kilpatrick: A Memoir," draft and printed copy, 1988 (Folder 47: 13)
  - "Wonderland Is a Strange Place," correspondence and printed copy, 1969 May (Folder 47: 14)
  - "Civil Rights and Humanization," draft, 1966 (Folder 48: 1)
  - "Youth Hosteling in Ohio," printed copy, 1941 February (Folder 48: 2)
  - Foreword to issue of Educational Method, on social travel, printed copy, 1941 February (Folder 48: 3)
  - "Conflicting Ideas on American Education Today," draft, 1967 (Folder 48: 4)
  - "Coordinating Educational Resources," draft, 1962 (Folder 48: 5)
  - "Highlights of the Junior High School Conference," draft, 1958 March 14-15 (Folder 48: 6)
  - "Education and the Resolution of Conflict," draft, 1968 (Folder 48: 7)
  - "The Great Debate and the Great Panic," draft, 1960 (Folder 48: 8)
  - "Education for the Eighties: The Crucial Problems," correspondence and drafts, 1978 (Folder 48: 9)
  - "What Should Be the Content of Curriculum?" printed copy, 1980 March (Folder 48: 10)
  - "Learning Democratic Human Relations," draft, 1950 (Folder 48: 11)
  - "Modern Education for the Changing Junior High School Years," draft and printed copy, 1966 May 6 (Folder 48: 12)
  - "On Models for Supervising Computerized Instruction," draft, 1968 March (Folder 48: 13)
  - "The Laboratory School: Its Rise and Fall?" correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1987 (Folder 48: 14)
  - "Reconstructing Disciplines and Changing the Curriculum," draft, 1964 October (Folder 48: 15)
  - "Pressures on Youth Today," draft, 1968 (Folder 48: 16)
  - Statement to the Senate and House Education and Judiciary Committees, Tennessee State Legislature, draft, 1957 January 15 (Folder 48: 17)
  - "Our Responsibility for Intercultural Education," draft, 1945 March 7 (Folder 48: 18)
  - "Social Change and Resultant Social Pressures," summary, 1966 September 28 (Folder 48: 19)
  - "Some Educational Practices and Programs Which Offer Promise for Greater Development of the Individual Pupil," 1960 (Folder 48: 20)
  - "Toward Democratic Human Relations," draft, 1956 (Folder 49: 1)
  - "Universities and Crises," draft, 1968 (Folder 49: 2)
  - "What Knowledge Is of Most Worth?" summary, 1955 (Folder 49: 3)
  - "Who Is Being Heard on Education Today?" draft, 1961 (Folder 49: 4)
- Reprints of articles used for instructional purposes, 1955-1959 (Folder 49: 5)
- Correspondence, 1976-1991
  - Writing for professional publication workshops, 1978-1990 (Folder 49: 6)
  - Travel and speaking engagements, 1976-1991
    - 1976-1984 (Folder 49: 7)
    - 1978-1979 (Folder 49: 8)
    - 1985-1986 (Folder 49: 9)
    - 1988-1991 (Folder 49: 10)
- Articles on William Van Til, 1977
  - Slapar, Trudie, 1977 (Folder 49: 11)
  - Morris, Robert C., 1977 (Folder 49: 12)
- Surveys supervised or conducted by William Van Til of school systems, 1948-1968
  - Springfield, Missouri, 1948 (Folder 50: 1)
  - Puerto Rico, 1959-1968 (Folder 50: 2-3)
  - Virgin Islands, 1963 (Folder 50: 4)
- Speeches and Writings, 1949-1981
  - "Alternative Reagans," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1981 February (Folder 50: 5)
  - "Anyone for International Work?" printed copy, 1971 November (Folder 50: 6)
  - "The Community Won't Stand for It," draft and printed copy, 1950 February (Folder 51: 1)
  - "Can Educators Trust Representatives of Government?" printed copy, 1976 February (Folder 51: 2)
  - "Cheaters of Children," printed copy, 1951 April (Folder 51: 3)
  - "The Climate of Fear," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1949 October (Folder 51: 4)
  - "The Compassionate Critics," printed copy, 1970 November (Folder 51: 5)
  - "Confrontation and Consequences," drafts and printed copy, 1971 May (Folder 51: 6)
  - "Convention Sites and the ERA," printed copy, 1978 June (Folder 51: 7)
  - "Curriculum for the Future," draft and printed copy, 1971 February (Folder 51: 8)
  - "Editorial Roulette," printed copy, 1978 February (Folder 51: 9)
  - "Education and Jimmy Carter," printed copy, 1976 November (Folder 51: 10)
  - "Environment versus Technology," draft and printed copy, 1972 December (Folder 51: 11)
  - "A Fighting Chance," printed copy, 1972 January (Folder 51: 12)
  - "Going the Second Mile," printed copy, 1974 November (Folder 51: 13)
  - "The Great American Cop-Out," draft and printed copy, 1972 October (Folder 51: 14)
  - "The Hair Decision of 1973," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1970 January (Folder 51: 15)
  - "He Went Back," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1950 March (Folder 51: 16)
  - "Horace Mann's Only Appearance on TV," printed copy, 1973 February (Folder 51: 17)
  - "The Ladder to Success in Universities," printed copy, 1951 May (Folder 51: 18)
  - "Last Column," draft and printed copy, 1950 May (Folder 51: 19)
  - "Let's Communicate Democratic Education," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1950 April (Folder 51: 20)
  - "Let Them Eat Space," printed copy, 1969 November (Folder 51: 21)
  - "Man vs. Machine," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1970 November (Folder 51: 22)
  - "The New Demonology," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1969 February (Folder 51: 23)
  - "People and Policies," draft, 1949 November (Folder 52: 1)
  - "Parallel Columns," printed copy, 1972 June (Folder 52: 2)
  - "The Raccoon Died," printed copy, 1970 March (Folder 52: 3)
  - "Reform of the High School in the Mid-1970s," draft and printed copy, 1975 March (Folder 52: 4)
  - "The Remarkable Culture of the American Educators," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1950 January (Folder 52: 5)
  - "Return to Wonderland," printed copy, 1975 December (Folder 52: 6)
  - "The Role of a Review Council," printed copy, 1976 May (Folder 52: 7)
  - "Scenarios for Education, Year 2000," printed copy, 1977 December (Folder 52: 8)
  - "The Second Coming of the One-Room Schoolhouse," printed copy, 1971 September (Folder 52: 9)
  - "Start Your Own Spring Conference," printed copy, 1975 June (Folder 52: 10)
  - "Stereotyping Youth and Negroes," printed copy, 1969 April (Folder 52: 11)
  - "Story of a Lake," printed copy, 1972 March (Folder 52: 12)
  - "Three Good Men," draft and printed copy, 1969 May (Folder 52: 13)
  - "To Walk with Others," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1970 May (Folder 52: 14)
  - "Toward Some Agreements at Geneva," printed copy, 1975 September (Folder 52: 15)
  - "Toward the Year 2000: Teacher Education," printed copy, 1979 September-October (Folder 52: 16)
  - "Tricentennial Speech, 2076: Two Versions," printed copy, 1976 September (Folder 52: 17)
  - "The Unknown Giant," printed copy, 1977 February (Folder 52: 18)
  - "Wanted: Effective Communication," correspondence and printed copy, 1977 September (Folder 52: 19)
  - "Welcome to the Club, Gentlemen," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1968 October (Folder 52: 20)
  - "What to Expect if Your Legislature Orders Literacy Testing," printed copy, 1978 April (Folder 52: 21)
  - "Whose Retirement?" draft and printed copy, 1977 May (Folder 52: 22)
- Article by Robert C. Morris, "William Van Til: Some Reflections by His Last Doctoral Student," printed copy, 1977 May (Folder 53: 1)
- Speeches and Writings, 1941-1975
  - "Why Educate?" printed copy, 1968 November (Folder 53: 2)
  - "Wonderland Is A Strange Place," draft and printed copy, 1969 May (Folder 53: 3)
  - "Working with William Heard Kilpatrick," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1956 December (Folder 53: 4)
  - "Writing for Educational Publication," printed copy, 1973 June (Folder 53: 5)
  - "Bali Ha'i," draft, 1965 (Folder 53: 6)
  - "Can a Working Mother Be a Good Mother?" correspondence and draft, 1964 (Folder 53: 7)
  - "Contemporary America Challenges Education," correspondence and drafts, 1961 (Folder 53: 8)
  - "The Counselors' Involvement in Curriculum," drafts, 1972 (Folder 53: 9)
  - "Criticisms of Secondary Education in the 1970s," draft, 1977 (Folder 53: 10)
  - "Education and Youth Today," draft, 1969 (Folder 53: 11)
  - "Fold Boater, Go Home," correspondence and draft, 1964 (Folder 53: 12)
  - "How Not to Pick a College," correspondence and draft, 1963 (Folder 54: 1)
  - "Human Relations," draft, 1962 (Folder 54: 2)
  - "The Indiana State University Laboratory School: A Proposal for Curriculum Development in the 1970s," draft, 1971 (Folder 54: 3)
  - "Is There a Chance?" draft, 1975 (Folder 54: 4)
  - "Models of Curriculum Planning-A New Look at Education," draft, 1969 (Folder 54: 5)
  - "Pressures on Youth Today," drafts, 1969 (Folder 54: 6)
  - "The Relevant Teacher," draft, 1972 (Folder 54: 7)
  - "The Second Law," correspondence and drafts, 1964 (Folder 54: 8)
  - "What's the Big Hurry?" notes, 1960 (Folder 54: 9)
  - "The Year 2000: The Principal," draft, 1971 (Folder 54: 10)
  - "Family Trip to Europe," draft, 1950 (Folder 54: 11)
  - "Directions in Which the Junior High School Is (or Should Be) Going," draft, 1960 (Folder 54: 12)
  - "Education for Democratic Values," draft, 1941 (Folder 54: 13)
  - "Democratic Values," draft, 1942 (Folder 54: 14)
  - Foreword to Louise E. Hock and Thomas J. Hill, The General Education Class in the Secondary School, draft, 1955 (Folder 54: 15)
  - Transcript of WNYU radio interview, 1964 (Folder 54: 16)
  - Transcript of WLIB radio interview, 1961 (Folder 54: 17)
  - "Education for Better Human Relations," transcript of televised lecture, 1960 May 14 (Folder 54: 18)
  - "Education for Fascism or Democracy," transcript of radio interview, 1942 July 4 (Folder 54: 19)
  - "A New Education in a New Age," transcript of radio address, 1948 March 15 (Folder 54: 20)
- Articles on William Van Til, 1955-1960 (Folder 54: 21-23)
- Speeches and Writings, 1941-1963
  - "Hosteling toward World Citizenship," draft, 1946 (Folder 55: 1)
  - "If We Intend to Change the Curriculum," correspondence, 1963 (Folder 55: 2)
  - "Learning the Ways of Democracy," draft, 1941 (Folder 55: 3)
  - "Promoting the In-Service Professional Development of the School Staff," draft, 1950 (Folder 55: 4)
  - Notes for a novel, 1950 (Folder 55: 5)
  - "Social and Cultural Developments Influence the Curriculum," draft, 1961 (Folder 55: 6)
  - "Community Book," draft, 1950 (Folder 55: 7-11)
- Correspondence, 1956-1964
  - Wilhelms, Fred T., 1964 (Folder 55: 12)
  - Educational Leadership, 1956 (Folder 55: 13)
  - The New York Times, 1957 (Folder 55: 14)
  - Letters sent from Iran to family and friends, 1962 (Folder 55: 15)
- Survey on teacher education in Iran, 1962 (Folder 55: 16)
- Speeches and Writings, 1928-1996
  - My Way of Looking at It, 1983-1996
    - Printed copy, 1983 (Folder 56: 1)
    - Draft of postscript for second edition, 1995 (Folder 56: 2)
    - Correspondence, 1994-1996 (Folder 56: 3)
  - "Pop," draft, 1928 (Folder 57: 1)
  - Untitled story, draft, 1928 (Folder 57: 2)
  - "A Few Minutes with Spike," draft, 1929 (Folder 57: 3)
  - "Haunted House," draft, 1929 (Folder 57: 4)
  - "Highlights," draft, 1929 (Folder 57: 5)
  - "Cornelius Vanderbilt," draft, 1930 (Folder 57: 6)
  - "How to Play the Line," draft, 1930 (Folder 57: 7)
  - "Little Guy," draft, 1930 (Folder 57: 8)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe: An Interpretation," draft, 1931 (Folder 57: 9)
  - "The Conflicting Character of Christ, the Man," draft, 1931 (Folder 57: 10)
  - "Rags," draft, 1931 (Folder 57: 11)
  - Report on Columbia Institute lecture series, draft, 1932 (Folder 57: 12)
  - "Loose," draft, 1932 (Folder 57: 13)
  - "Homecoming," draft, 1932 (Folder 57: 14)
  - "Ivan Turgenev: Born Onlooker," draft, 1932 (Folder 57: 15)
  - "Two Literary Epicureans: James Branch Cabell and Anatole France," draft, 1933 February (Folder 57: 16)
  - "Education," printed copy, 1933 May (Folder 57: 17)
  - "Toward Better Social Science in the College," draft, 1935 (Folder 57: 18)
  - "The Left Looks at The Sunday Herald Tribune," draft, 1935 (Folder 57: 19)
  - "Paris in the Spring," travel diary, 1936 (Folder 57: 20)
  - "My Bay," draft, 1936 (Folder 57: 21)
  - "Back Where He Came from," draft, 1936 (Folder 57: 22)
  - "Veteran of the Wars," draft, 1936 (Folder 57: 23)
  - "Myopia in the Black Forest," draft, 1936 (Folder 57: 24)
  - "James T. Farrell," draft, 1936 (Folder 57: 25)
  - "Mark Van Doren," draft, 1936 (Folder 57: 26)
  - "Czechoslovakian Sketches," draft, 1936 August 17 (Folder 57: 27)
  - "Take What You've Got," draft, 1936 August 19 (Folder 57: 28)
  - "Deep and Brown," draft, 1937 (Folder 57: 29)
  - "Depression Generation," draft, 1937 (Folder 57: 30)
  - "Mississippi," draft, 1937 (Folder 57: 31)
  - "National Reports on High School Curriculum: Some Comparisons," draft, 1984 (Folder 57: 32)
  - "How It Looks to William Van Til," correspondence and transcript of interview, 1989 (Folder 57: 33)
  - "Script for a Scene in a Hitchcock Film," draft, 1994 February 23 (Folder 57: 34)
- Announcement, address list, and schedule for writing workshop, 1980 (Folder 57: 35)
- Speeches and Writings, 1983-1997
  - "Some Things I Had to Learn," correspondence and printed copy, 1997 (Folder 58: 1)
  - My Way of Looking at It, 1983-1997
    - Correspondence, 1994-1996 (Folder 58: 2)
    - Drafts, 1983-1996 (Folder 58:)
      - First edition, 1983 (Folder 58: 4-5)
      - Second edition, 1996 (Folder 58: 6)
      - Second edition, 1996 (Folder 59: 1-2)
    - Proofs of second edition, 1996 (Folder 59: 6-7)
    - Printed copy, 1996 (Folder 59: 8)
    - Reviews, 1997 (Folder 59: 9)